Finding aid to the Louise Rood Papers CA.MS.00322
Smith College Archives
Louise Rood Papers
1937-1983
Smith College Archives
Rood, Louise, 1910-1964
CA.MS.00322
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
Instructor of music 1937-1958, Professor of Music 1958-1964. Contains biographical information, photographs, correspondence, sheet music, and lecture notes.
Biographical / Historical
Louise Miles Rood was born in 1910 to James and Myrtle Merrill Rood in Easton, Pennsylvania. She obtained her bachelor degree in 1929 from the University of Wisconsin. Around 1934, Rood taught for three years at Sweet Briar College on a Julliard Extension Fellowship. In 1937 Rood was hired as an instructor of music at Smith. While teaching full time, she completed her master degree in 1942 at Smith College. In 1945, she received a diploma from the Julliard Graduate School of Music.
Rood taught a wide range of musical subjects, from theory to practical, focusing on the violin and the viola. She performed as a soloist with Smith groups and elsewhere around New England and the Midwest. Rood also wrote the book Introduction to the Orchestra Score. During many summers, Rood taught sessions at the University of Iowa, the University of Michigan, and Mary Washington College. In 1958, she became a professor at Smith.
Rood died suddenly of a cerebral hemorrhage on February 7, 1964. Following her death, the annual Louise Rood Memorial Concert was established in her honor.
Scope and Contents
Contains biographical information, photographs, correspondence, sheet music, and lecture notes covering Rood's career as a faculty member at Smith College and as a performing musician.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Louise Rood papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Rood, Louise, 1910-1964
- Biographical Materials, 1948-1983; undated (Box 990, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1943-1964; undated (Box 990, Folder 2)
- Lecture Notes: Counterpoint, 1955-1957; undated (Box 990, Folder 3)
- Lecture Notes: Music 22, 1950-1958; undated (Box 990, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes: Music 23, 1947 (Box 990, Folder 5)
- Lecture Notes: Music 31a, 1954-1955 (Box 990, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes: Music 35a, 1946 (Box 991, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes: Music 35, 1947 (Box 991, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes: Orchestration - The Instruments, 1956-1958; undated (Box 991, Folder 9)
- Notes on 17th Century, undated (Box 991, Folder 10)
- Notes on Giovanni Battista Vitali, undated (Box 991, Folder 11)
- Notes on Ornamentation, 1959 (Box 991, Folder 12)
- Violin Notes, undated (Box 991, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous Notes, 1951-1956; undated (Box 991, Folder 14)
- Miscellaneous: Asher on the Horn - Ed London, undated (Box 991, Folder 15)
- Sheet Music, undated (Box 991, Folder 16)
- Photographs, 1952-1953; undated (Box 991, Folder 17)